Equal Rights Amendment Campaign Archives Project records SSC.MS.00310
Sophia Smith Collection
Equal Rights Amendment Campaign Archives Project records
1970-1985
Sophia Smith Collection
SSC.MS.00310
46 boxes (29.75 linear feet)
Documentation program. The Equal Rights Amendment Campaign Archives Project Records include correspondence, speeches, legal documents, photographs, press releases, reports, articles, interview transcripts, audio and video tapes, legislative records, logbooks, notes, documentary footage, and memorabilia. The bulk of the records comprise audiovisual materials from two documentaries: "Who Will Protect the Family," Victoria Costello's PBS documentary based on the 1982 North Carolina ERA campaign; and "Fighting for the Obvious" based on the Chicago, Illinois, ERA campaign produced by Virago Video, and ERACAP. There is also considerable material relating to the National Organization for Women's work to pass the Equal Rights Amendment. Additional ERA-related materials collected by Beth Leopold are included. Notable individuals included in the documentary footage are: Susan Cantinia, Dennis Cuddy, Donald Deuster, Frances Fitzgerald, Jesse Helms, Wilma Scott Heide, Peggy Madigan, Lamarr Mooneyham, Kathy Railsback, Phyllis Schlafly, Ellie Smeal, Gloria Steinem, and Monica Faith Stewart.
Biographical / Historical
The Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) was first introduced in the U.S. Congress in 1923. It was introduced in every session of Congress after that for nearly half a century. In 1971 the House of Representatives approved the proposed amendment. The Senate approved the amendment a year later. The issue was sent to the state legislatures and twenty states ratified the ERA almost immediately (Alaska, Colorado, Delaware, Hawaii, Idaho, Iowa, Kansas, Kentucky, Maryland, Massachusetts, Michigan, Nebraska, New Hampshire, New Jersey, New York, Rhode Island, Tennessee, Texas, West Virginia, and Wisconsin). In 1973 Connecticut, South Dakota, Oregon, Minnesota, New Mexico, Vermont, Washington, and Wyoming ratified; Nebraska voted to rescind its ratification. Over the next few years, Maine, Montana and Ohio voted to ratify and Tennessee voted to rescind. In an effort to gain the additional three votes necessary for ratification, groups with many pro-ERA supporters boycotted states that had failed to ratify the Amendment. As the deadline for ratification loomed (22 March 1979), Representative Elizabeth Holtzman (D-NY) introduced a bill to extend the deadline for ratification. In October of 1978, Congress set a new deadline for the ERA--30 June 1982. In 1980 Ronald Reagan became the first president since the Equal Rights Amendment was sent to the states to oppose the ERA. On 30 June 1982 the ERA died, falling three states short of the necessary three-fourths ratification.
Beth Leopold worked on the National Organization for Women (NOW) campaign to ratify the ERA. After its defeat, she sought to ensure that the story of the fight for ratification would be preserved and began the Equal Rights Amendment Campaign Archives Project (ERACAP). The goal of the ERACAP was to "collect and process oral history and photographic materials relating to the ERA campaign between the years 1970 and 1982." The focus of the collecting was on the experiences of participants in the local, state, and national levels of the campaign.
The aim of the original project was to interview 150-200 people involved in the pro or anti-ERA work using archival quality open reel audiotape and to make typed transcripts of the interviews. There were also plans to create an index of the subjects covered in the interviews, along with photographs and a directory for additional materials related to the ERA campaign. Because funding for the project ran out in 1984, the oral history interviews were never created; however, Beth Leopold acted as intermediary between the Sophia Smith Collection and two documentary filmmakers to house their tapes and accompanying printed matter within the ERACAP collection. "Who Will Protect the Family?" was completed and aired on PBS in 1982. "Fighting for the Obvious" (Virago Video, 1982) was also completed, but it is uncertain whether it was shown by a major media outlet. In addition, Leopold's own ERA-related material came with the ERACAP materials.
Scope and Contents
The ERACAP Records consist of 29.75 linear feet and are primarily related to the fight to ratify the Equal Rights Amendment between 1972 and 1982. Types of materials include correspondence, speeches, legal documents, photographs, press releases, reports, journal and newspaper articles, transcripts of interviews, audiocassettes, videocassettes, legislative records, logbooks, notes, documentary footage, and memorabilia.
The bulk of the records comprise audiovisual materials documenting the ERA fights in Illinois and North Carolina from two documentaries, Fighting for the Obvious and Who Will Protect the Family?. There is also considerable material relating to the National Organization for Women's work to pass the Equal Rights Amendment.
Notable individuals included in the documentary footage are: Alan Alda, Birch Bayh, Susan Cantinia, Midge Costanza, Dennis Cuddy, Donald Deuster, Frances Fitzgerald, Jake Garn, Jesse Helms, Wilma Scott Heide, Peggy Madigan, Lamarr Mooneyham, Kathy Railsback, Phyllis Schlafly, Eleanor Smeal, Gloria Steinem, and Monica Faith Stewart. A portion of the footage for each documentary has been reformatted to DVD viewing copies.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series:
I. ERACAP ADMINISTRATION
II. NATIONAL ORGANIZATION FOR WOMEN AND THE ERA
III. WHO WILL PROTECT THE FAMILY? DOCUMENTARY FILES
IV. ERA DEFEAT
V. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
Conditions Governing Access
The Records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the exception of audiovisual materials that have not been reformatted for use by researchers. Viewing copies for selected footage are available on DVD.
Additional Formats
Some original videotaped recordings have been copied to digital files for research use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Lynn Kanter (Virago Video) donated the audiovisual materials from Fighting for the Obvious in 1984. Beth Leopold donated her personal papers and the records of ERACAP as well as Victoria Costello's materials relating to Who Will Protect the Family? to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1988.
Related Materials
Additional materials documenting the Equal Rights Amendment can be found in the papers of the Blake Family, Dori Jacobson, Dorothy Kenyon, Alma Lutz, G.J. Stillson MacDonnell, Gloria Steinem, Linda Stout, Mary van Kleeck, the records of the Young Women's Christian Association, and the Women's Rights and Employment Collections. The majority of the records of the National Organization for Women and the ERA can be found at the Schlesinger Library at Harvard University.
Equal rights amendments--Illinois--History--Sources; Equal rights amendments--North Carolina--History--Sources; Equal rights amendments--United States--History--Sources; National Organization for Women--History--Sources; Oral history--methodology; Women's rights--United States--History--Sources; Family--Social aspects--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Feminism--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Feminists--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Equal Rights Amendment Campaign Archives Project; Leopold, Beth; Costello, Victoria; Kanter, Lynn; Ephemera; correspondence; articles; Audiotapes; Videotapes; clippings; Publicity; Transcripts; photographs; Card files; Oral histories; Logbooks; Moral Majority, Inc.; Fitzgerald, Frances, 1940-; McAllister, Beth; Schlafly, Phyllis; Costello-Clunn, Victoria; Equal Rights Amendment Campaign Archives Project (ERACAP)
- SERIES I. ERACAP ADMINISTRATION ‡SERIES I. ERACAP ADMINISTRATION, (1981-85); .5 linear ft.; 1981-85
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Beth Leopold's administrative records of the Equal Rights Amendment Campaign Archives Project, including the project proposal, ERACAP's financial and equipment needs, and correspondence with the Sophia Smith Collection. Most of the unrelated publications by history organizations and guides to oral histories have been removed from the collection.
  - Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Project proposal, 1983-84; undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Advisory board, 1983; undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters of support, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - ERA materials to collect, 1981-83 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Financial materials
    - Expenses, 1983; undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Sources of funding, 1983; undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Grantsmanship Center, 1983; undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Tax-exempt status, 1984-85; undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1983-85 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      General
      [see also Smith College]
    - Memberships, 1982-84 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Equipment and services, 1982-83; undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Smith College, 1982-85
      - General, 1982-85 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Alternative Career Conference, April 15-16, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- SERIES II. NATIONAL ORGANIZATION FOR WOMEN AND THE ERA, 1970-83
  Beth Leopold's work at the National Organization for Women is documented in this series. Media projects played a large role in NOW's efforts to pass the ERA in the fifteen states where it hadn't yet passed. The ERA Countdown campaign materials include photocopies of images dating back to the early twentieth century that were selected for a film to document the struggle for the ERA, with the bulk of the images covering the 1970s and early 1980s. Other media-related projects for NOW can be found in the materials related to the Legal Defense and Education Fund. This series also covers several major marches and rallies for the ERA. The Capitol March for ERA focuses mostly on Chicago, where Leopold directed her energies. This series also includes subject files, memorabilia, and a bibliography of newspaper clippings from the New York Times related to the ERA from 1970 through 1982.
  - Articles, pamphlets, and reports about the ERA, 1979-80, undated ==ERA Countdown Campaign (Box 1, Folder 15)
    [see also SERIES III. - Pro-ERA Countdown]
    - General, 1981-82; undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Celebrity support, 1980-82; undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Film, 1968-80; undated
      - Film images, 1-643 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
      - Photo log (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - " Film"
        - "NOW Music Selections:" audiocassette tape, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
          [digital file available]
      - ==Images, 1974; undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
        - LA Photo Log Images, September 18, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
        - Correspondence, memos, and reports, 1981-82; undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Speeches, 1982; undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Virginia's ERA Struggle, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Fundraising kit, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Legal Defense and Education Fund
    - General, 1978-81; undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Staff members, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Projection Equal Education Rights (PEER), 1982 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Media Project
      - General, 1980-82; undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Advertising
        - Equipment, 1978-81; undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
        - Outdoor advertising, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
        - Public Service Announcements (PSAs)
          - Production companies, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
          - Sample scripts, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
        - Notes, 1981; undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
        - Radio, 1981-82 (Box 3, Folder 8)
        - Television, 1981-82 (Box 3, Folder 9)
          [see also Public Service Announcements]
      - Artwork, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Conferences and consultations
        - Freestyle evaluation conference, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
        - Michigan Media Project conference, 1980-81 (Box 3, Folder 12)
        - State broadcasting action workshop, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
        - Vanguard Network proposal, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 2)
        - Women in the media study, 1980-83; undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
        - Other conferences, 1980-81 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - ERA Awareness Week, 1981-82 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Pilot Program, 1979-80; undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Purchase orders, 1981-82 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Status reports, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Leadership mailing lists, 1979-82; undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Marches, rallies, and other events
    - Springfield, IL: Rally, 16 May 1976 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Washington, DC:, March; 9 Jul 1978 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Washington, DC: ERA Inauguration Watch, 20 Jan 1980 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - San Antonio, TX: National Conference, 3-5 Oct 1980 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Utah: Missionary Project, 9 Apr-19 Jul 1981 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - ERA Walkathons, Aug 1981 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Washington, DC: National Conference, 10-12 Oct 1981 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Illinois: Fast for Justice, May 1982 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Capitol March for ERA, 6 June 1982 (Box 4)
      - Kits (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - Illinois
        - Contracts (Box 5, Folder 1)
        - General notes (Box 5, Folder 2)
        - Letters to ERA supporters (Box 5, Folder 3)
        - Musicians (Box 5, Folder 4)
        - Material order forms (Box 5, Folder 5)
        - Newspaper clippings (Box 5, Folder 6)
        - Organizational materials (Box 5, Folder 7)
        - Outreach (Box 5, Folder 8)
        - Planning materials (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
        - Recruitment (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Washington, DC: Rally, 30 Jun 1982 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - PAC/Woman Walkathon, 28 Aug 1982 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Post-ERA response by NOW: Vote out the opposition, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Other state/local activities, 1980-82 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Unidentified ERA events: negatives and proof sheets, undated (Box 5, Folder 16-17)
  - Media Reform Committee
    - General, 1979-81; undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Communications technology, 1980; undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Federal Communications Commission and discrimination, 1979-81; undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Memorabilia
    - Buttons, 1982; undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Ribbons, posters, and ERA "business cards,", 1977-82; undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Stickers, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - General, 1981-82; undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - NOW Convention, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - NOW Press releases, 1980-82 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Protests
    - Movie: Windows, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Appointment of Rex E. Lee as Solicitor General, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Subject files
    - Draft case/women in the military, 1980-81 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Reagan, Ronald: newspaper clippings, 1980-83 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Reproductive rights, 1980-82; undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Other women's issues, 1980-83; undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
- SERIES III. WHO WILL PROTECT THE FAMILY? DOCUMENTARY FILES‡SERIES III. WHO WILL PROTECT THE FAMILY? DOCUMENTARY FILES, 1974-82; undated
  [see also SERIES V. -Who Will Protect the Family?]
  This series is composed of the administrative and subject files of Victoria Costello, the director for Who Will Protect the Family?, an hour length color PBS documentary that examines the motivations, beliefs, and larger goals of the two movements fighting for and against the Equal Rights Amendment, focusing in particular on anti-ERA activist, Marilyn DeVries. And pro-ERA activist, Beth McAllister. Although the documentary specifically focuses on the three year battle to pass the ERA in North Carolina, the materials in this series relate to legislation, statistics, and organizations on both the state and national levels, as well as subjects that extend beyond the Equal Rights Amendment. Only a few transcripts from the film footage are in the collection; nevertheless, the few that exist provide valuable insight into the motivations of individuals fighting for and against the passage of the amendment, as do the brief summaries of selected footage in the Appendix. The audiovisual materials from the documentary are found in SERIES V. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS.
  - Video logs
    - Raleigh, NC, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Pro/anti-ERA groups and people, 1981 (Box 13)
  - Transcripts, Aug 1981: audiocassettes 1-6 (Box 13, Folder 14-19)
  - Publicity, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Notes and questions, 1981; undated (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Archival visuals (North Carolina), 1981; undated (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - North Carolina contacts, 1981; undated (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Anti-ERA
    - General: articles and newspaper clippings, 1979-82; undated (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - American Family Institute, 1980; undated (Box 25)
  - American Life Lobby, 1979-81; undated (Box 26)
    [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS]
    - Christianity and Politics conference (8-9 May 1981), 1976-81, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Cuddy, Dennis, 1978-81; undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - DeVries, Marilyn, 1980; undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Family Protection Reporter, 1979-81 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Marshner, Connie (Box 7)
      [see also Family Protection Reporter]
    - Moral Majority, 1980-81; undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
      [see also oversize box 12]
    - The Right Woman, 1979-81; undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Schlafly, Phyllis (Box 7)
      [see also Stop ERA]
    - Stop ERA, 1980-82 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Other anti-ERA groups, 1979-82; undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Pro-ERA
    - General: articles, newspaper clippings, and speeches, 1978-81; undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Congressional Union, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - ERA America, 1978-80 (Box 7, Folder 11-12)
    - ERA Countdown, 30 Jun 1981 (Box 7, Folder 13)
      [see also SERIES II. NOW and the ERA Countdown Campaign]
    - Johnson, Sonya (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - McAllister, Beth, 1981; undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Ms. Meeting, 26 May 1981 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - North Carolina Council of Churches, 1981; undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Pamphlets, 1978-80; undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Shoulder to Shoulder March for the ERA, 2 May 1981 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - New York Times ERA timeline, 1970-82: card file (Box 7a)
  - North Carolina, 1981 legislative session
    - Abortion (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Background information, 1979-81; undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Day care, 1981 legislative session (Box 3)
    - Equal Rights Amendment (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Marital property distribution (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Other bills (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - U.S. Congress
    - Abortion/Human Life Amendment, 1980-81; undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
      [see also Family Protection Act]
    - Economic Equity Act, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Equal Rights Amendment, 1978; 1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Family Protection Act, 1981 (Box 3)
      - CRS Report and Analysis (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Legislation (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Summaries (Box 12)
    - Social Security, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Voting records, 1980-81 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Subjects and statistics
    - Abortion, 1979-81; undated (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Apparel and tobacco industry, 1978-81 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Day care, 1980-81; undated (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Divorce statistics, 1981; undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Domestic violence, 1977-81 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Families, 1978-82
      - General, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - National, 1978-82 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Juvenile criminal behavior, 1979-81 (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
  - North Carolina statistics, 1978-81; undated
    - Employment, 1978-81 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - General, 1974-81 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Original grids, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Personal Income, 1973-81 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Planned Parenthood: activities and criticisms of, 1980-81; undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
    [see also Sex Education]
  - Sex education, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Teenage pregnancy, 1976-81; undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Textbooks, 1974-81; undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Women, 1975-81; undated (Box 10, Folder 6-7)
- SERIES IV. ERA DEFEAT ‡SERIES IV. ERA DEFEAT, (1982-84; undated); .25 linear ft.; 1982-84
  This small series contains published and unpublished articles and essays that examine the Equal Rights Amendment, its defeat, and its supporters and opponents.
  - Susan Harding articles and papers, 1981-1983 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - ERA essays in OAH newsletter, 1982-83 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - "The Equal Rights Amendment: Anatomy of a Failure," PS, Fall 1982 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Jennifer Jackman/Tamar Raphael project, 1983-84 (Box 11, Folder 4-6)
    [note: most of the audiotapes and transcripts from this project are located in the Women's Rights Collection; see also Correspondence in SERIES I]
  - Until Justice is Done: The Fight for the ERA, Spring 1983 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- SERIES V. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS, 1978-82; undated
  This large series forms the bulk of the collection and includes 30 hours of videotape for Fighting for the Obvious (over 100 tapes), a documentary about the ERA fight in Illinois, as well as several hundred ¾ inch Umatics and ½ inch Betas from the PBS documentary Who Will Protect the Family?, which documents the ERA fight in North Carolina.
  A sample of original video footage for both documentaries has been are available as digital copied to digital files for access. See Appendix for descriptions of digitized video.
  - DVD viewing copies of unedited documentary footage
    [These videos are available as digital files See Appendix for full descriptions.]
    - Who Will Protect the Family?
      - Nos. 1-78 (Box 13)
      - Nos. 79-123 (Box 14)
    - Fighting for the Obvious
      - Nos. 1-44 (Box 14)
      - Nos. 45-72 (Box 15)
  - DVD preservation masters (Box 16-17)
    Conditions Governing Access
    [CLOSED]
  - Digital Beta tapes (Box 18-28)
  - Original ¾" UMatic videotapes (Box 29-45)
    [For full list of original tapes, contact the SSC]
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - American Life Lobby: A.LL. About Issues, Oct 1980-Mar1981 (Box 12)
  - "ERA YES" sign (Box 12)
  - Moral Majority Report (5 issues), 1980-81 (Box 12)
  - Moral Majority: poster, undated (Box 12)
  - "The Life and Times of Rosie the Riveter": invitation mock-up, 1981 (Box 12)
  - "Tell Me a Riddle": invitation mock-up, 1981 (Box 12)
  - SAM: Soldier, Sailor, Airman, Marine, Feb 1980: "Women in Combat?...Let's Get Serious" (Box 12)
  - Sash for 1980 ERA march (Box 12)